<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>blog.harterrt.com</title><link href="https://blog.harterrt.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://blog.harterrt.com/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://blog.harterrt.com/</id><updated>2017-10-26T00:00:00-07:00</updated><entry><title>Evaluating New Tools</title><link href="https://blog.harterrt.com/new_tools.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-10-26T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-10-26T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Ryan T. Harter</name></author><id>tag:blog.harterrt.com,2017-10-26:/new_tools.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;At Mozilla, we're still relatively early in our data science journey.
As such, we're always evaluating new tools to improve our analysis workflow
(&lt;a href="http://jupyter.org/"&gt;jupyter&lt;/a&gt; vs. &lt;a href="http://rmarkdown.rstudio.com/"&gt;Rmd&lt;/a&gt;),
or make our infrastructure more usable
(our home-rolled &lt;a href="https://github.com/mozilla/telemetry-analysis-service"&gt;ATMO&lt;/a&gt;
vs. &lt;a href="https://databricks.com/"&gt;databricks&lt;/a&gt;),
or scale our knowledge
(&lt;a href="https://medium.com/airbnb-engineering/scaling-knowledge-at-airbnb-875d73eff091"&gt;knoledge-repo&lt;/a&gt;.
vs. &lt;a href="https://www.gitbook.com/"&gt;gitbook&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of these tools look like …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;At Mozilla, we're still relatively early in our data science journey.
As such, we're always evaluating new tools to improve our analysis workflow
(&lt;a href="http://jupyter.org/"&gt;jupyter&lt;/a&gt; vs. &lt;a href="http://rmarkdown.rstudio.com/"&gt;Rmd&lt;/a&gt;),
or make our infrastructure more usable
(our home-rolled &lt;a href="https://github.com/mozilla/telemetry-analysis-service"&gt;ATMO&lt;/a&gt;
vs. &lt;a href="https://databricks.com/"&gt;databricks&lt;/a&gt;),
or scale our knowledge
(&lt;a href="https://medium.com/airbnb-engineering/scaling-knowledge-at-airbnb-875d73eff091"&gt;knoledge-repo&lt;/a&gt;.
vs. &lt;a href="https://www.gitbook.com/"&gt;gitbook&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of these tools look like they have compelling wins over our existing solutions.
But when we build a demo,
our users ignore some tools and rave about others.
Why?
I think it's because some of &lt;strong&gt;the costs of adopting a new tool are subtle&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unless your new tool is a perfect match for the problem at hand (very rare)
I need to spend time learning, coding, or configuring the tool to work for me. 
At the same time,
I have &lt;strong&gt;work due today&lt;/strong&gt; and an existing set of tools that are good enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What follows are some thoughts I have when deciding whether to adopt a new tool.
Maybe they will help you (or future me) &lt;strong&gt;debug problems with adoption&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What am I taking home?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your new tool is internal-only, uncommon in the industry, or expensive
I'm going to be less likely to adopt it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this case, anything I learn while adopting your tool
is &lt;strong&gt;unlikely&lt;/strong&gt; to be &lt;strong&gt;valuable to future employers&lt;/strong&gt;.
I think of my 
&lt;a href="https://esimoney.com/two-huge-reasons-why-your-career-matters/"&gt;career as an asset&lt;/a&gt;,
so if I get to do work that builds &lt;strong&gt;transferable skills&lt;/strong&gt;,
I count that as &lt;strong&gt;part of my compensation&lt;/strong&gt;.
On the other hand,
if I'm writing glue scripts to deal with idiosyncrasies in an internal tool,
I'm missing out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think this is a major reason
&lt;strong&gt;why large tech companies open source internal technologies&lt;/strong&gt;. 
Consider 
&lt;a href="https://code.facebook.com/projects/552007124892407/presto/"&gt;prestodb&lt;/a&gt;
or &lt;a href="https://golang.org/"&gt;golang&lt;/a&gt;.
How much would it suck to spend time learning these tools
if they were internal-only?
When you leave the company all of that skill becomes useless.
By open-sourcing these technologies,
you've just &lt;strong&gt;increased your employee compensation without spending a dollar&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How long will I have access?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your tool is closed source or expensive,
I'm going to hesitate before spending any time with it.
I depend on my tools and it hurts to lose them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is why I prefer Python or R to MATLAB.
I can use my experience with Python or R build side projects
that scratch my own itch.
MATLAB is expensive, so I don't have that benefit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How long will it be relevant?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if the tool is open source,
I want it to be configurable and composable.
This ensures it can grow with me.
I have no idea what the tech landscape will look like in 10 years,
but I do know it will be different.
&lt;strong&gt;I want your tool to play nicely with technology that doesn't exist yet&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even better, if your tool is configurable and composable
it is probably going to take me much less time to get comfortable with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Composability is one of my bigger complaints about Jupyter.
Jupyter is a great tool for exploratory analysis,
but I don't want to use your GUI for editing code.
I'm much happier when I get to use my own tool chain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, Jupyter's saving grace is that it's configurable.
I'm working on a tool that will make it easy to develop
python packages and Jupyter notebooks side-by-side.
Hopefully, this will give us the best of both worlds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All this to say,
I'm going to carefully gauge the lifetime value of any new tool I adopt.
If your users are ignoring a new tool you've created,
&lt;strong&gt;look carefully for hidden restrictions to lifetime value&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand,
if your tool solves a critical enough problem,
I'll stand barefoot in the snow to use it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does this all make any sense?
Am I missing something important?
Why do you roll your eyes when someone tries to sell you a new tool?&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Documentation Style Guide</title><link href="https://blog.harterrt.com/docs-style-guide.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-08-24T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-08-24T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Ryan T. Harter</name></author><id>tag:blog.harterrt.com,2017-08-24:/docs-style-guide.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I just wrote up a style guide for our 
&lt;a href="https://docs.telemetry.mozilla.org"&gt;team's documentation&lt;/a&gt;.
The documentation is rendered using Gitbook and hosted on Github Pages.
You can find the 
&lt;a href="https://github.com/mozilla/firefox-data-docs/pull/41"&gt;PR here&lt;/a&gt;
but I figured it's worth sharing here as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Style Guide&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Articles should be written in
&lt;a href="https://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/syntax"&gt;Markdown&lt;/a&gt;
(not &lt;a href="http://asciidoctor.org/docs/asciidoc-syntax-quick-reference/"&gt;AsciiDoc&lt;/a&gt;).
Markdown is usually …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I just wrote up a style guide for our 
&lt;a href="https://docs.telemetry.mozilla.org"&gt;team's documentation&lt;/a&gt;.
The documentation is rendered using Gitbook and hosted on Github Pages.
You can find the 
&lt;a href="https://github.com/mozilla/firefox-data-docs/pull/41"&gt;PR here&lt;/a&gt;
but I figured it's worth sharing here as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Style Guide&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Articles should be written in
&lt;a href="https://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/syntax"&gt;Markdown&lt;/a&gt;
(not &lt;a href="http://asciidoctor.org/docs/asciidoc-syntax-quick-reference/"&gt;AsciiDoc&lt;/a&gt;).
Markdown is usually powerful enough and is a more common technology than AsciiDoc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Limit lines to &lt;strong&gt;100 characters&lt;/strong&gt; where possible.
Try to split lines at the end of sentences.
This makes it easier to reorganize your thoughts later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This documentation is meant to be read digitally.
Keep in mind that people read digital content much differently than other media.
Specifically, readers are going to skim your writing,
so make it easy to identify important information&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use &lt;strong&gt;visual markup&lt;/strong&gt; like &lt;strong&gt;bold text&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;code&gt;code blocks&lt;/code&gt;, and section headers.
Avoid long paragraphs.
Short paragraphs that describe one concept each makes finding important information easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please squash your changes  into meaningful commits  and follow these
&lt;a href="https://chris.beams.io/posts/git-commit/"&gt;commit message guidelines&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="mozilla"></category><category term="documentation"></category></entry><entry><title>Beer and Probes</title><link href="https://blog.harterrt.com/probes.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-08-23T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-08-23T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Ryan T. Harter</name></author><id>tag:blog.harterrt.com,2017-08-23:/probes.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Quick post to clear up some terminology.
But first, an analogy to clear up my thinking:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Analogy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Temperature control is a big part of brewing beer.
Throughout the brewing process I use a thermometer
to measure the temperature of the soon-to-be beer.
Because I take several temperature readings throughout the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Quick post to clear up some terminology.
But first, an analogy to clear up my thinking:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Analogy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Temperature control is a big part of brewing beer.
Throughout the brewing process I use a thermometer
to measure the temperature of the soon-to-be beer.
Because I take several temperature readings throughout the brewing process,
one brew will result in a list of a half dozen temperature readings.
For example, I take a mash temperature,
then a sparge temperature,
then a fermentation temperature.
The units on these measurements are always in Fahrenheit,
but their interpretation is different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Rub&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this example, I would call the thermometer a "probe".
The set of all temperature readings share a "data type".
Each temperature reading is a "measurement" which is stored in a given "field".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the SFO workweek I uncovered some terminology I found confusing.
Specifically, we use the word "probe" to refer to data we collect.
I haven't encountered this usage outside of Mozilla.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, I'd suggest we call histograms and scalars "data types".
A "probe" is a unit of client-side code that collects a measurement for us.
A single "field" could be be a column in one of our datasets (like &lt;code&gt;normalized_channel&lt;/code&gt;).
A measurement would be a value from a single field from a single ping (like the string "release").&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Bad Tools are Insidious</title><link href="https://blog.harterrt.com/bad-tools.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-06-15T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-06-15T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Ryan T. Harter</name></author><id>tag:blog.harterrt.com,2017-06-15:/bad-tools.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is my first job making data tools that other people use.
In the past, I've always been a data scientist -
a consumer of these tools.
I'm learning a lot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last quarter, I learned that bad tools are often hard to spot even when they're damaging productivity.
I sum this …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is my first job making data tools that other people use.
In the past, I've always been a data scientist -
a consumer of these tools.
I'm learning a lot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last quarter, I learned that bad tools are often hard to spot even when they're damaging productivity.
I sum this up by saying that &lt;strong&gt;bad tools are insidious&lt;/strong&gt;.
This may be &lt;a href="https://sivers.org/obvious"&gt;obvious to you&lt;/a&gt; but I'm excited by the insight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Bad tools are hard to spot&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spent some time working directly with analysts building ETL jobs.
I found some big usability gaps with our tools
and I was surprised I wasn't hearing about these problems from our analysts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I looked back to previous jobs where I was on the other side of this equation.
I remember being totally engrossed in a problem and excited to finding a solution.
All I wanted were tools good enough to get the job done.
I didn't care to reflect on how I could make the process smoother.
I wanted to explore and interate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I dug into analyses this quarter, I had a different perspective.
I was working with the intention of improving our tools
and the analysis was secondary.
It was much easier to find workflow improvements this way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Design_of_Everyday_Things"&gt;Design of Everyday Things&lt;/a&gt; 
Donald notes that users tend to blame themselves when they have difficulty with tools.
That's probably part of the issue here as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Bad tools hurt&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If our users aren't complaining, is it really a problem that needs to get fixed?
I think so.
We all understand that bad tools hurt our productivity.
However, I think we tend to underestimate the value of good tools when we do our mental accounting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Say I'm working on a new ETL job that takes ~5 minutes to test by hand
but ~1 minute to test programatically.
By default, I'd value implementing good tests at 4 minutes per test run.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a huge underestimate!
Testing by hand introduces a context shift, another chance to get distracted,
and another chance to fall out of flow.
I'll bet a 5 minute distraction can easily end up costing me 20 minutes of productivity on a good day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your tools should be a joy to use.
The better they work, the easier it is to stay in flow, be creative, and stay excited.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;In Summary&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't expect your users to tell you how to improve your tools.
You're probably going to need to
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eating_your_own_dog_food"&gt;eat your own dogfood&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Literature Review: Writing Great Documentation</title><link href="https://blog.harterrt.com/lit-review.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-02-03T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2017-02-03T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Ryan Harter</name></author><id>tag:blog.harterrt.com,2017-02-03:/lit-review.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;div id="preamble"&gt;
&lt;div class="sectionbody"&gt;
&lt;div class="paragraph"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m working on a big overhaul of my team&amp;#8217;s documentation.
I&amp;#8217;ve noticed writing documentation is a difficult thing to get right.
I haven&amp;#8217;t seen any great example for a data product, either.
I don&amp;#8217;t have much experience in this area,
so I decided to review …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;div id="preamble"&gt;
&lt;div class="sectionbody"&gt;
&lt;div class="paragraph"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m working on a big overhaul of my team&amp;#8217;s documentation.
I&amp;#8217;ve noticed writing documentation is a difficult thing to get right.
I haven&amp;#8217;t seen any great example for a data product, either.
I don&amp;#8217;t have much experience in this area,
so I decided to review what&amp;#8217;s already been written about creating great documentation.
This is a summary of what I&amp;#8217;ve found,
both for my own reference and to help others understand my thought process.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="sect1"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="_findings"&gt;Findings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="sectionbody"&gt;
&lt;div class="paragraph"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I should note, all the literature I could find focused on documenting software products.
I am willing to bet that a data product is going to have different documentation needs than most software products.
But, this is as good a place to start as any.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="sect2"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="_structure_amp_what_to_write"&gt;Structure &amp;amp; What to Write&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="paragraph"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Most seem to agree that a &lt;strong&gt;README&lt;/strong&gt; is a critical piece of documentation.
The README is usually comprised of two key parts:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="olist arabic"&gt;&lt;ol class="arabic"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A quick introduction explaining what this project is, why the reader should
  care, and whether it&amp;#8217;s worth investing time to understand it better.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A simple tutorial to get the reader started and give a feel for what the tool
  actually does.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="paragraph"&gt;&lt;p&gt;If the reader decides they want to learn more,
there should be a set of &lt;strong&gt;topical guides or tutorials&lt;/strong&gt; which comprise the bulk of the documentation.
Think of each of these guides as a class focused on teaching your student (reader) a single skill.
Reading all of these guides should take "someone who has never seen your product and make them an expert user". [&lt;a href="#TDT"&gt;TDT&lt;/a&gt;]
With that in mind, make sure there&amp;#8217;s some sense of order to these lessons (easy to hard).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="paragraph"&gt;&lt;p&gt;If your reader gets this far, they are now very comfortable with your product.
From here, they need high-quality &lt;strong&gt;reference material&lt;/strong&gt;.
In my experience, this is the most common documentation provided,
but it is needed latest in the process and only by the most advanced users!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="paragraph"&gt;&lt;p&gt;When I started this research,
I was having a hard time figuring out how we were going to separate our
prose documentation from our development notes.
Now I see that these are just different stages in this learning process.
First we explain what it is, then how to use it, and finally, how to extend it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="sect2"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="_style"&gt;Style&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="paragraph"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Most articles suggest adopting a style guide to make it easier for a user to read your documentation.
The writing should pull you through the document and feel natural.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="paragraph"&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you want your documentation to read naturally, you should try to become a better writer.
This comes as cold solace to most folks, since I need my documentation now
and I can&amp;#8217;t wait 10,000 hours to become an expert writer, but it&amp;#8217;s worth mentioning.
The overwhelming consensus is that the best way to become a better writer is to &lt;strong&gt;write a lot&lt;/strong&gt;.
If you want to write great documentation, consider building habits that will make you a great writer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="paragraph"&gt;&lt;p&gt;As with programming, maintaining a consistent style will help readers understand your documentation naturally.
Note, the important word here is "consistent".
&lt;strong&gt;Choose a style and stick with it&lt;/strong&gt;.
This sounds obvious, but I rarely find corporate documentation with consistent style across tutorials.
Have a style guide and enforce it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="paragraph"&gt;&lt;p&gt;As you choose your style guide, be aware that most of the advice is focused on physical media.
Your documentation is probably going to be read digitally,
so your readers will have different expectations.
Specifically, readers are going to skim your writing, so make it easy to identify important information.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="paragraph"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Use &lt;strong&gt;visual markup&lt;/strong&gt; like bold text, code blocks, call-outs
(e.g &lt;a href="http://www.methods.co.nz/asciidoc/chunked/ch16.html#X22"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="http://getbootstrap.com/components/#alerts"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;), and section headers.
Similarly, avoid long paragraphs.
Short paragraphs that describe one concept each makes finding important information easier.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="paragraph"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Most guides suggest keeping a &lt;strong&gt;conversational tone&lt;/strong&gt;.
This makes the guide more approachable and easier to read.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="paragraph"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Everyone seems to agree that &lt;strong&gt;you should have an editor&lt;/strong&gt;.
In fact, Jacob Kaplan-Moss dedicated an entire article to this point [&lt;a href="#YNAE"&gt;JKM 3&lt;/a&gt;].
If you don&amp;#8217;t have access to an editor,
review your own work thrice then ask for someone else&amp;#8217;s review before publishing.
Try adjusting your margins to force the text to re-flow.
It&amp;#8217;s a very effective way to catch spelling or grammatical mistakes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="sect2"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="_tools"&gt;Tools&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="paragraph"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ll start this section with a warning.
Tools often receive an undue amount of attention, especially from programmers.
With documentation, &lt;strong&gt;writing is the hard, important work&lt;/strong&gt;.
It&amp;#8217;s important to use good tools, but make sure you&amp;#8217;re not
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Law_of_triviality"&gt;bike shedding&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="paragraph"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Your documentation should be stored in &lt;strong&gt;plain text and in version control&lt;/strong&gt;.
Most of your documentation is going to be written by programmers,
and programmers have powerful tools for manipulating text.
Using anything besides plain text is a frustration that makes it less
likely they&amp;#8217;ll enjoy writing documentation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="paragraph"&gt;&lt;p&gt;You should have a &lt;strong&gt;process for reviewing changes&lt;/strong&gt; to the documentation.
Review will help maintain a consistent voice across your documentation
and will provide useful feedback to the writer.
Think of how useful code reviews are for improving your programming.
I&amp;#8217;d jump at the chance to get feedback from an expert writer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="paragraph"&gt;&lt;p&gt;You &lt;strong&gt;should not use a wiki&lt;/strong&gt; for documentation.
Wikis make documentation "everyone&amp;#8217;s responsibility",
which really means it&amp;#8217;s nobody&amp;#8217;s responsibility.
Without this responsibility, wikis tend to decay into a web of assorted links without any sense of order or importance.
Wikis make it impossible to maintain a consistent voice throughout your documentation.
Finally, it&amp;#8217;s difficult to get review for your work before publishing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="paragraph"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Recognize that automatically-generated documentation isn&amp;#8217;t a replacement for hand-crafted prose.
Remember that the bulk of your documentation should be tutorials meant to slowly ramp up your users to expert status.
Docstrings have very little utility in this process.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="sect1"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="_resources"&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="sectionbody"&gt;
&lt;div class="paragraph"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Most of what I&amp;#8217;ve summarized here came from very few sources.
I highly recommend you read the following articles if you&amp;#8217;re interested in learning more:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="ulist"&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a id="SL"&gt;&lt;/a&gt; [TDT]: &lt;a href="http://stevelosh.com/blog/2013/09/teach-dont-tell/"&gt;Teach, Don&amp;#8217;t Tell&lt;/a&gt; (Steve Losh)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a id="JKM 1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt; [JKM 1]: &lt;a href="https://jacobian.org/writing/what-to-write/"&gt;What to Write&lt;/a&gt; (Jacob Kaplan Moss)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a id="JKM 2"&gt;&lt;/a&gt; [JKM 2]: &lt;a href="https://jacobian.org/writing/technical-style/"&gt;Technical Style&lt;/a&gt; (Jacob Kaplan Moss)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a id="JKM 3"&gt;&lt;/a&gt; [JKM 3]: &lt;a href="https://jacobian.org/writing/editors/"&gt;You Need an Editor&lt;/a&gt; (Jacob Kaplan Moss)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="paragraph"&gt;&lt;p&gt;For later reference, I also reviewed these articles to form opinions about
general consensus outside of the primary sources above:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="ulist"&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href="http://www.americanscientist.org/issues/id.877,y.0,no.,content.true,page.1,css.print/issue.aspx"&gt;The Science of Scientific Writing&lt;/a&gt;
  (George Gopen, Judith Swan): Good overview of how to structure a paper so
  readers find information where they expect it to be
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href="http://www.writethedocs.org/"&gt;WriteTheDocs.org&lt;/a&gt;, specifically
  &lt;a href="http://www.writethedocs.org/guide/writing/beginners-guide-to-docs/"&gt;A Beginner&amp;#8217;s Guide to Writing Docs&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href="https://github.com/noffle/art-of-readme"&gt;Art of README&lt;/a&gt;: An arguement for
  writing good READMEs and a template to help you get started
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!topic/scala-internals/r2GnzCFc3TY"&gt;Scala Documentation Discussion&lt;/a&gt;
  A discussion of why Scala&amp;#8217;s official documentation is so bad
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href="http://r-pkgs.had.co.nz/vignettes.html"&gt;Vignettes&lt;/a&gt; (Hadley Wickham): Hadley
  is a rockstar in the R universe. This is an article from his style guide for
  writing R package documentation. This is the closest I could come to finding
  documentation advice for data products.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href="http://steve-yegge.blogspot.com/2008/09/programmings-dirtiest-little-secret.html"&gt;Programming&amp;#8217;s Dirtiest Little Secret&lt;/a&gt;
  (Steve Yegge): Steve Yegge on why it&amp;#8217;s important to type well
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href="https://byrslf.co/writing-great-documentation-44d90367115a#.nenvaqeng"&gt;Writing Great Documentation&lt;/a&gt;:
  This article comments on documentation&amp;#8217;s propensity towards kippleization.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.gnu.org/prep/standards/standards.html#GNU-Manuals"&gt;GNU Manual Style Guide&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="mozilla"></category><category term="documentation"></category></entry><entry><title>Is moving to the Bay Area worth it?</title><link href="https://blog.harterrt.com/is-moving-to-the-bay-area-worth-it.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-12-14T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2016-12-14T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Ryan T. Harter</name></author><id>tag:blog.harterrt.com,2016-12-14:/is-moving-to-the-bay-area-worth-it.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I came across &lt;a href="http://blog.triplebyte.com/does-it-make-sense-for-programmers-to-move-to-the-bay-area"&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt; on the front page of Hacker News yesterday.
The author argues that Bay Area housing prices may be high, but the salary increase probably makes it worth while.
The author pulls together some interesting data to make their point,
but I have major &lt;strong&gt;issues with …&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I came across &lt;a href="http://blog.triplebyte.com/does-it-make-sense-for-programmers-to-move-to-the-bay-area"&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt; on the front page of Hacker News yesterday.
The author argues that Bay Area housing prices may be high, but the salary increase probably makes it worth while.
The author pulls together some interesting data to make their point,
but I have major &lt;strong&gt;issues with the analysis&lt;/strong&gt;.
In fact, the data seem to be &lt;strong&gt;showing the opposite trend&lt;/strong&gt;,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Summary of findings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's the important information from the article:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The author reviews median tech worker salaries from the BLS, Indeed, and GlassDoor and finds:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;engineers at top tech companies in the Bay Area stand to make between $15,000
and $33,000 more per year than engineers at top tech companies in Seattle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Comparing median monthly rent from Zillow, the author finds:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;median rent is about $1400-$1500 a month (or roughly $17,000-$18,000 a year)
higher in the Bay Area than in the Seattle metro area&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The author then concludes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;higher Bay Area salaries at least cover the costs of higher rents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Taxes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most obvious error is that this analysis completely &lt;strong&gt;ignores all taxes&lt;/strong&gt;.
I &lt;a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=13178880"&gt;pointed this out&lt;/a&gt; in the comments,
but the conversation exclusively focused on the difference between WA and CA state taxes.
I think it's important to note that this estimate also ignores &lt;em&gt;federal&lt;/em&gt; taxes as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, consider a Seattle salary of $100k and a Bay Area salary of $133k.
Assuming a federal tax rate of 33%, that $33k tax difference will be reduced to $22k takehome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$133k * (1-0.33) - $100 * (1-0.33) ~= $22k&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since WA does not have a state income tax and CA has a significant income tax,
you'll also end up paying just a bit over $10k in state taxes.
This drops the take home pay increase to $12k total.
And, according to the data, this is at the high end of the scale!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In reality, there's no way we'll cover the $17k rent difference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Median Rental Price&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few folks argued the use of a median isn't appropriate here.
I agree to a point, but I think it's probably a good first approximation,
especially since the author restricted their data to tech salaries in each market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, I do have once concern here.
I'm willing to bet that &lt;strong&gt;Seattle renters can get more space for their median
rental than a Bay Area renter can get for the Bay Area median rental&lt;/strong&gt;.
As rent prices increase, renters will adjust by increasing the amount the spend
on rent and reducing the value of thier apartment.
In economic terms, a consumer's demand for an apartment is not perfectly inelastic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I saw this first hand when I moved to the Bay Area.
Prices were generally higher than what I was used to, so I adapted by increasing my
monthly rent, downsizing my apartment, and increasing my commute length.
I also noticed more of my peers sharing apartments or houses who wouldn't do so in lower COL areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After accounting for taxes and reviewing the metrics used for rental costs, the
salary increase from moving to the Bay Area is &lt;strong&gt;very unlikely to cover the
increase in housing costs&lt;/strong&gt;, especially for similar housing.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="critique"></category></entry><entry><title>Announcing the Cross Sectional Dataset</title><link href="https://blog.harterrt.com/announcing-the-cross-sectional-dataset.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-11-14T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2016-11-14T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Ryan T. Harter</name></author><id>tag:blog.harterrt.com,2016-11-14:/announcing-the-cross-sectional-dataset.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm happy to announce a new telemetry dataset!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Cross Sectional dataset makes it easy to describe our users by providing
summary statistics for each client.  Like the Longitudinal table, there's one
row for each client_id in a 1% sample of clients.  However, the Cross Sectional
dataset simplifies your analysis …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm happy to announce a new telemetry dataset!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Cross Sectional dataset makes it easy to describe our users by providing
summary statistics for each client.  Like the Longitudinal table, there's one
row for each client_id in a 1% sample of clients.  However, the Cross Sectional
dataset simplifies your analysis by replacing the longitudinal arrays with
summary statistics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dataset is now available in
&lt;a href="https://sql.telemetry.mozilla.org/queries/1669/source"&gt;STMO&lt;/a&gt;.  You can find
more information in &lt;a href="https://github.com/mozilla/telemetry-batch-view/blob/master/docs/choosing_a_dataset.md#cross-sectional"&gt;the
documentation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take a look and let me know if you have any question or suggestions for new
columns!&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Meta Documentation</title><link href="https://blog.harterrt.com/meta-documentation.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-11-03T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2016-11-03T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Ryan T. Harter</name></author><id>tag:blog.harterrt.com,2016-11-03:/meta-documentation.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;You'll see a lot of posts coming down the line on documentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We surveyed our customers last quarter and asked where our data pipeline was lacking.
It turns out the most painful part of using our data pipeline, is reading the documentation.
I've been interesting in learning how to write …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;You'll see a lot of posts coming down the line on documentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We surveyed our customers last quarter and asked where our data pipeline was lacking.
It turns out the most painful part of using our data pipeline, is reading the documentation.
I've been interesting in learning how to write great documentation for a while,
so I volunteered to spend a significant amount of time reworking our documentation this quarter. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To summarize, our team tries to make telemetry data useful.
Some of us build tools to make accessing the data easy,
others work on processing the data and making it available in an efficient and understandable format.
Last quarter I worked on the latter, pipelining hte data to make the format better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year, I'll be working as a data ambassador.mentor,
going out to teams, identifying their data needs, and helping them reach their goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Data is an incredibly useful tool.
It takes a lot of the guesswork out of building useful projects.
However, even though we have a great product, it's useless if our users don't understand how to use it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have a great tool for our customers, but it's not worth the energy to learn about it. 
It's easier to do a one off analysis that is kind-of right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have a data product or tool without documentation, it's more likely than not that someone is misusing your data.
The hardest part of making data useful is understanding how it was collected and in what situations it is appropriate. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[TOC]&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="documentation mozilla"></category></entry><entry><title>Why Markdown?</title><link href="https://blog.harterrt.com/why-markdown.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-11-03T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2016-11-03T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Ryan T. Harter</name></author><id>tag:blog.harterrt.com,2016-11-03:/why-markdown.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;[TOC]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week I finished a &lt;a href="https://github.com/mozilla/telemetry-batch-view/pull/128"&gt;pull
request&lt;/a&gt; that moved
some documentation from &lt;a href="https://wiki.mozilla.org/Telemetry/LongitudinalExamples"&gt;mozilla's
wiki&lt;/a&gt; to a &lt;a href="https://github.com/mozilla/telemetry-batch-view/blob/master/docs/longitudinal_examples.md"&gt;github
repository&lt;/a&gt;.
It took a couple of hours of editing and toying with pandoc to get right, but
when I was done, I realized the benefits were difficult to see.  So, I decided …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;[TOC]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week I finished a &lt;a href="https://github.com/mozilla/telemetry-batch-view/pull/128"&gt;pull
request&lt;/a&gt; that moved
some documentation from &lt;a href="https://wiki.mozilla.org/Telemetry/LongitudinalExamples"&gt;mozilla's
wiki&lt;/a&gt; to a &lt;a href="https://github.com/mozilla/telemetry-batch-view/blob/master/docs/longitudinal_examples.md"&gt;github
repository&lt;/a&gt;.
It took a couple of hours of editing and toying with pandoc to get right, but
when I was done, I realized the benefits were difficult to see.  So, I decided
to write them out for posterity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Better Process&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only way to edit our wiki is through the web front end which causes some
major problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For one, You're always editing the production version and there's no way to get
review before publishing. That's obviously not great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, your edits need to be submitted quickly - like within an hour, usually.
Since you're editing in a web form there's no good way to save your edits
locally.  Even worse, there's no good way to settle merge conflicts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With markdown, I can develop my revisions over the course of weeks and preview
them locally.  When it's time to publish I get review from my peers, which
makes my documentation more readable and helps me improve as an engineer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Better Tools&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have powerful tools for manipulating text so using a simple web form to edit
technical documentation seems absurd to me.  With markdown, I get the joy of
using my favorite text editor in my favorite development environment&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;One less tool&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our team is already using Markdown for our README's and Github provides a much
better UX for revison control.  By moving to Markdown for our user facing
documentation, we have one less tool and syntax we need to depend on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The documentation sits next to the code&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Storing your documentation with your code has a lot of great benefits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Syncronization&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pull requests can include simultanious changes to code and documentation, which
makes it more likely they'll stay in sync. Both because you don't need to go
edit them elsewhere and because it can become a review requirement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Discoverability&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keeping the docs next to the code helps with discoverability. Your
code and your documentation should supplement each other. Keeping them close
together is only reasonable.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="documentation"></category><category term="mozilla"></category></entry><entry><title>Working over SSH</title><link href="https://blog.harterrt.com/working-over-ssh.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-09-05T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2016-09-05T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Ryan T. Harter</name></author><id>tag:blog.harterrt.com,2016-09-05:/working-over-ssh.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;[TOC]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working over SSH can be impossibly frustrating if you're not using the right tools. 
I promised my teammates a write-up how I work over ssh.
Using these tools will make it significantly easier / more fun to work with a remote linux system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Tools&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="https://tmux.github.io/"&gt;tmux&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, tmux is …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;[TOC]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working over SSH can be impossibly frustrating if you're not using the right tools. 
I promised my teammates a write-up how I work over ssh.
Using these tools will make it significantly easier / more fun to work with a remote linux system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Tools&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="https://tmux.github.io/"&gt;tmux&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, tmux is the single tool most important getting work done over SSH.
tmux does a lot of really cool things, but the most relevant feature to this discussion is session persistence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Session Persistence&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;tmux sessions can be detached and reattached at will.
That means you can &lt;strong&gt;execute some long running command on an AWS cluster, kill the ssh session, and the command will keep running&lt;/strong&gt;.
Later, you can reconnect to the cluster and session, it will be as if you hadn't left.
So much nicer than cussing out your flaky WiFi connection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Start a new session named &amp;quot;foo&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Opens a new shell as a subprocess&lt;/span&gt;
tmux new -s foo

&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Do stuff ...&lt;/span&gt;
sleep &lt;span class="m"&gt;100&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Kill the session, returning you to the original shell&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# with ctrl-b d&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Reconnect to the tmux session&lt;/span&gt;
tmux at -dt foo

&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Still waiting!!&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;More often, I use tmux just to save my place when I need to wrap up for the day.
Next morning, I can reattach my session and I'm already looking at the most relevant files for today's work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Multiplexing&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is what tmux's was built to do. I think persistence is just a nice side effect.
tmux allows you to open a bunch of terminals in a single ssh connection.
Think of tmux as a tiling window manager for the terminal.
Here's a screen shot of how I developed this blog post:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.harterrt.com/images/example-tmux-session.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's all in one terminal window.
On the left I have a process serving up drafts of this document and on the right I have my text editor.
The extra context is indispensable when trying to figure out WTF is going on with a failing job.
For example, monitoring an &lt;code&gt;sbt ~test&lt;/code&gt; process on the left while making edits on the right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/andsens/homeshick"&gt;Homeshick&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Configuring a new machine is a PITA.
For a while, I saw all configuration changes as a liability and refused to customize my environment.
After all, I'd eventually have to redo all of these configs when I get a new machine.
But, your tools should be a joy to use, and Homeshick makes this a non-issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Homeshick pulls all of your dotfiles into a central git repository and handles linking these files to the right location.
Now, I can &lt;strong&gt;setup a new Ubuntu machine within ~5 minutes&lt;/strong&gt; with all of my dotfiles intact.
When I connect to a machine for the first time, I grab &lt;a href="https://github.com/harterrt/TIL/blob/master/linux/new-machine.md"&gt;this snippet&lt;/a&gt; and all of the initialization is done.
Even better, the meaningful config changes I make on my work machine magically materialize on my personal machine and VPS with a simple &lt;code&gt;git pull&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://github.com/andsens/homeshick"&gt;README&lt;/a&gt; is pretty good and it shouldn't take longer than ~15 minutes to set up.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="tools"></category></entry><entry><title>Strange Spark Error</title><link href="https://blog.harterrt.com/strange-spark-error.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-08-26T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2016-08-26T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Ryan T. Harter</name></author><id>tag:blog.harterrt.com,2016-08-26:/strange-spark-error.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;[TOC]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spend the better part of last week debugging a Spark error, so I figure it's worth writing up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;The Bug&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I added the &lt;a href="https://github.com/harterrt/spark-failure/blob/master/failure.scala"&gt;this very simple view&lt;/a&gt; to our &lt;a href="https://github.com/mozilla/telemetry-batch-view/tree/master/src/main/scala/com/mozilla/telemetry/views"&gt;batch views repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;package&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;com.mozilla.telemetry.views&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="k"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;org.apache.spark.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nc"&gt;SparkConf&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nc"&gt;SparkContext&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;org.apache.spark …&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;[TOC]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spend the better part of last week debugging a Spark error, so I figure it's worth writing up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;The Bug&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I added the &lt;a href="https://github.com/harterrt/spark-failure/blob/master/failure.scala"&gt;this very simple view&lt;/a&gt; to our &lt;a href="https://github.com/mozilla/telemetry-batch-view/tree/master/src/main/scala/com/mozilla/telemetry/views"&gt;batch views repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;package&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;com.mozilla.telemetry.views&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="k"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;org.apache.spark.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nc"&gt;SparkConf&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nc"&gt;SparkContext&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;org.apache.spark.sql.hive.HiveContext&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="k"&gt;case&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nc"&gt;Base&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;client_id&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kt"&gt;String&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="k"&gt;case&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nc"&gt;Target&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;client_id&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kt"&gt;String&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="k"&gt;object&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nc"&gt;FailingView&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;generateCrossSectional&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;base&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kt"&gt;Base&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nc"&gt;Target&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;base&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;client_id&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="o"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;main&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;args&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kt"&gt;Array&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;String&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;])&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kt"&gt;Unit&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;val&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;sparkConf&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nc"&gt;SparkConf&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;().&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;setAppName&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;this&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;getClass&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;getName&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;sparkConf&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;setMaster&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;sparkConf&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;get&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;spark.master&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;local[*]&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;val&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;sc&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nc"&gt;SparkContext&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;sparkConf&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="k"&gt;val&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;hiveContext&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nc"&gt;HiveContext&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;sc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;hiveContext.implicits._&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="k"&gt;val&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;ds&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;hiveContext&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;sql&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;SELECT * FROM longitudinal&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;selectExpr&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;client_id&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;as&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;Base&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;val&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;output&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;ds&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;map&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;generateCrossSectional&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="n"&gt;println&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;=&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;80&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;\n&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;output&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;count&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;\n&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;=&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;80&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="o"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When I run this on an ATMO cluster, I observe the following error:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Exception in thread &amp;quot;main&amp;quot; org.apache.spark.SparkException: Job aborted due to stage failure: Task 24 in stage 1.0 failed 4 times, most recent failure: Lost task 24.3 in stage 1.0 (TID 64, ip-172-31-8-250.us-west-2.compute.internal): java.io.IOException: org.apache.spark.SparkException: Failed to get broadcast_2_piece0 of broadcast_2
    at org.apache.spark.util.Utils$.tryOrIOException(Utils.scala:1222)
    at org.apache.spark.broadcast.TorrentBroadcast.readBroadcastBlock(TorrentBroadcast.scala:165)
    at org.apache.spark.broadcast.TorrentBroadcast._value$lzycompute(TorrentBroadcast.scala:64)
    at org.apache.spark.broadcast.TorrentBroadcast._value(TorrentBroadcast.scala:64)
    at org.apache.spark.broadcast.TorrentBroadcast.getValue(TorrentBroadcast.scala:88)
    at org.apache.spark.broadcast.Broadcast.value(Broadcast.scala:70)
    at org.apache.spark.scheduler.ShuffleMapTask.runTask(ShuffleMapTask.scala:65)
    at org.apache.spark.scheduler.ShuffleMapTask.runTask(ShuffleMapTask.scala:41)
    at org.apache.spark.scheduler.Task.run(Task.scala:89)
    at org.apache.spark.executor.Executor$TaskRunner.run(Executor.scala:214)
    at java.util.concurrent.ThreadPoolExecutor.runWorker(ThreadPoolExecutor.java:1145)
    at java.util.concurrent.ThreadPoolExecutor$Worker.run(ThreadPoolExecutor.java:615)
    at java.lang.Thread.run(Thread.java:745)
Caused by: org.apache.spark.SparkException: Failed to get broadcast_2_piece0 of broadcast_2
    at org.apache.spark.broadcast.TorrentBroadcast$$anonfun$org$apache$spark$broadcast$TorrentBroadcast$$readBlocks$1$$anonfun$2.apply(TorrentBroadcast.scala:138)
    at org.apache.spark.broadcast.TorrentBroadcast$$anonfun$org$apache$spark$broadcast$TorrentBroadcast$$readBlocks$1$$anonfun$2.apply(TorrentBroadcast.scala:138)
...
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't get much information from this message, and searching for this error yields a variety of threads with half solved solutions.
My hunch is this message pops up for a variety of issues.
What's even more strange is that this function runs successfully when we read local data using a SQLContext.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Fixes?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I dug in for a while and I found two possible solutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of calling generateCrossSectional, we can just inline the meat of the function and everything works.
This isn't a great solution, because this function is going to grow over the next month and I don't want to maintain the behemoth. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a few refactors, I found that the function will run if I change the scope of the HiveContext val.
Take a look at &lt;a href="https://github.com/harterrt/spark-failure/blob/master/fixed.scala"&gt;this solution&lt;/a&gt;, which successfully runs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;package&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;com.mozilla.telemetry.views&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="k"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;org.apache.spark.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nc"&gt;SparkConf&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nc"&gt;SparkContext&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;org.apache.spark.sql.hive.HiveContext&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="k"&gt;case&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nc"&gt;Base&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;client_id&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kt"&gt;String&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="k"&gt;case&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nc"&gt;Target&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;client_id&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kt"&gt;String&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="k"&gt;object&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nc"&gt;PassingView&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;generateCrossSectional&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;base&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kt"&gt;Base&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nc"&gt;Target&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;base&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;client_id&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="o"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;main&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;args&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kt"&gt;Array&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;String&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;])&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kt"&gt;Unit&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;val&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;sparkConf&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nc"&gt;SparkConf&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;().&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;setAppName&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;this&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;getClass&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;getName&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;sparkConf&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;setMaster&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;sparkConf&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;get&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;spark.master&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;local[*]&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;val&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;sc&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nc"&gt;SparkContext&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;sparkConf&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="k"&gt;val&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;hiveContext&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nc"&gt;HiveContext&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;sc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;hiveContext.implicits._&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="k"&gt;val&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;ds&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;hiveContext&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;sql&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;SELECT * FROM longitudinal&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;selectExpr&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;client_id&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;as&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;Base&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;val&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;output&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;ds&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;map&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;generateCrossSectional&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="n"&gt;println&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;=&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;80&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;\n&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;output&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;count&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;\n&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;=&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;80&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="o"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h1&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This solution isn't totally gratifying since I'm still unclear on what's causing the error, but I'm stopping here.
The cluster this was tested on is still running Spark 1.6, which apparently has some known issues.
Once we upgrade to 2.0 I may take another look.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="spark"></category><category term="scala"></category></entry></feed>