<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>blog.harterrt.com</title><link>http://blog.harterrt.com/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2016 00:00:00 -0700</lastBuildDate><item><title>Meta Documentation</title><link>http://blog.harterrt.com/meta-documentation.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;You'll see a lot of posts coming down the line on documentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We surveyed our customers last quarter and asked where our data pipeline was lacking.
It turns out the most painful part of using our data pipeline, is reading the documentation.
I've been interesting in learning how to write great documentation for a while,
so I volunteered to spend a significant amount of time reworking our documentation this quarter. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To summarize, our team tries to make telemetry data useful.
Some of us build tools to make accessing the data easy,
others work on processing the data and making it available in an efficient and understandable format.
Last quarter I worked on the latter, pipelining hte data to make the format better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year, I'll be working as a data ambassador.mentor,
going out to teams, identifying their data needs, and helping them reach their goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Data is an incredibly useful tool.
It takes a lot of the guesswork out of building useful projects.
However, even though we have a great product, it's useless if our users don't understand how to use it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have a great tool for our customers, but it's not worth the energy to learn about it. 
It's easier to do a one off analysis that is kind-of right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have a data product or tool without documentation, it's more likely than not that someone is misusing your data.
The hardest part of making data useful is understanding how it was collected and in what situations it is appropriate. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="toc"&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Ryan T. Harter</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.harterrt.com,2016-11-03:meta-documentation.html</guid><category>documentation mozilla</category></item><item><title>Why Markdown?</title><link>http://blog.harterrt.com/why-markdown.html</link><description>&lt;div class="toc"&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#better-process"&gt;Better Process&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#better-tools"&gt;Better Tools&lt;/a&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#one-less-tool"&gt;One less tool&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#the-documentation-sits-next-to-the-code"&gt;The documentation sits next to the code&lt;/a&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#syncronization"&gt;Syncronization&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#discoverability"&gt;Discoverability&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week I finished a &lt;a href="https://github.com/mozilla/telemetry-batch-view/pull/128"&gt;pull
request&lt;/a&gt; that moved
some documentation from &lt;a href="https://wiki.mozilla.org/Telemetry/LongitudinalExamples"&gt;mozilla's
wiki&lt;/a&gt; to a &lt;a href="https://github.com/mozilla/telemetry-batch-view/blob/master/docs/longitudinal_examples.md"&gt;github
repository&lt;/a&gt;.
It took a couple of hours of editing and toying with pandoc to get right, but
when I was done, I realized the benefits were difficult to see.  So, I decided
to write them out for posterity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="better-process"&gt;Better Process&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only way to edit our wiki is through the web front end which causes some
major problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For one, You're always editing the production version and there's no way to get
review before publishing. That's obviously not great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, your edits need to be submitted quickly - like within an hour, usually.
Since you're editing in a web form there's no good way to save your edits
locally.  Even worse, there's no good way to settle merge conflicts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With markdown, I can develop my revisions over the course of weeks and preview
them locally.  When it's time to publish I get review from my peers, which
makes my documentation more readable and helps me improve as an engineer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="better-tools"&gt;Better Tools&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have powerful tools for manipulating text so using a simple web form to edit
technical documentation seems absurd to me.  With markdown, I get the joy of
using my favorite text editor in my favorite development environment&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="one-less-tool"&gt;One less tool&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our team is already using Markdown for our README's and Github provides a much
better UX for revison control.  By moving to Markdown for our user facing
documentation, we have one less tool and syntax we need to depend on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-documentation-sits-next-to-the-code"&gt;The documentation sits next to the code&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Storing your documentation with your code has a lot of great benefits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="syncronization"&gt;Syncronization&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pull requests can include simultanious changes to code and documentation, which
makes it more likely they'll stay in sync. Both because you don't need to go
edit them elsewhere and because it can become a review requirement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="discoverability"&gt;Discoverability&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keeping the docs next to the code helps with discoverability. Your
code and your documentation should supplement each other. Keeping them close
together is only reasonable.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Ryan T. Harter</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.harterrt.com,2016-11-03:why-markdown.html</guid><category>documentation</category><category>mozilla</category></item></channel></rss>