<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>blog.harterrt.com</title><link href="https://blog.harterrt.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://blog.harterrt.com/feeds/not-mozilla.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://blog.harterrt.com/</id><updated>2018-01-02T00:00:00-08:00</updated><entry><title>Productivity Systems for Stress Management</title><link href="https://blog.harterrt.com/productivity_systems.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-01-02T00:00:00-08:00</published><author><name>Ryan T. Harter</name></author><id>tag:blog.harterrt.com,2018-01-02:productivity_systems.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Over the years, I've developed a pretty involved productivity system.
It was originally based on &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Getting-Things-Done-Stress-Free-Productivity/"&gt;Getting Things Done&lt;/a&gt;,
but now it's grown to include the good bits from other systems.
It's involved, but I love it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I get a lot of comments,
especially on the little black book I keep in my back pocket.
I hear people say they want to get organized so they can be more productive,
but I think that misses the mark.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting organized may make you more productive,
but the real benefit is that &lt;strong&gt;getting organized makes you less stressed&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The intro to "&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Getting-Things-Done-Stress-Free-Productivity/"&gt;Getting Things Done&lt;/a&gt;" does a great job of explaining this.
The gist is that filling your consciousness with list of things you have to do &lt;strong&gt;later&lt;/strong&gt;
distracts from what you're doing &lt;strong&gt;now&lt;/strong&gt;.
Irrelevant stuff keeps popping into your head and causing stress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of trying to remember all the stuff you need to do,
build a trusted system that will remember for you.
Then all you need to do is set up a few habits to remind you to look at your system.
&lt;strong&gt;Your brain is bad at remembering, but it's good at habits&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the past few years, my main goal has been increasing how much I enjoy my work.
&lt;strong&gt;Cutting the stress out of my workday was a huge improvement to my work satisfaction&lt;/strong&gt;.
If you're feeling stressed or burnt out,
I highly recommend looking at whether a productivity system would help.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry></feed>